why does it feel like the Market's
against you and every time you open a
trade it just loses well there's
probably a good reason for that and it
might not be what you think I can tell
you it's not just bad luck or that the
market gods are against you well maybe a
little bit in your case just kidding
whenever I see people saying things like
the trade didn't go to plan or every
trade I open is a loss when I dig a bit
deeper It's usually the same situation
most Traders structure their trades with
favorable as symmetric risk reward
ratios it's what everyone's told to do
and in most cases it makes the most
sense for the situation because that's a
big reason why you're deciding it's an
opportunity in the first place so what
do I mean by asymmetric risk reward it's
really simple it means that one side of
the potential outcomes is larger than
the other so for example if we have a
favorable asymmetric risk reward ratio
it might mean that we're risking a loss
of one to make a potential profit of
four so in Practical terms if we look at
this trade as an example example we have
our stop- loss set to 20 Pips and the
potential profit is 80 Pips which means
it's a 1 to four risk reward now just to
be clear most of my trades are
asymmetric so I'm not saying that that
is inherently a problem the real issue
here is perception let me explain let's
say that you're taking that trade from
the example before but the problem is
you have absolutely no Edge in the
market which let's be honest is the case
for most Traders out there usually
following some illogical trading
approach so with no Edge the probability
of it being a loss is 80% in other words
if you traded like that a 100 times over
80 of the times you'd expect it to be a
loss and just 20 times a profit now
instead let's say that you do have an
edge and that's why you're taking that
trade smart move well it would take a
Monumental trade of the century to shift
the probabilities enough that the most
likely outcome is a profit rather than
loss instead we can think of it this way
the concept of having an edge is not
that it means a profit is more likely
than a loss on an individual trade it
just means that the probabilities are
favorable enough that you'll have a
profit overall if you take that sort of
trade time and time again what I'm
describing here is basically the
expectancy of your trade and the
combination of all of this is what leads
to your Traders equation if your Traders
equation is positive then great you're a
profitable Trader and if it's negative
you've got some work to do but what is
not showing you is that you have more
profitable trades than losing trades now
if this concept is something you're
struggling with or you want to
understand better I've got something
that will help in the description box
you'll find a link to my free trading
Master Class where I'll explain to you
the logical formula for successful
trading that focuses on probabilities
and assessing the expectancy of our
trades for the long term it's full of
insights and it will give you a whole
new perspective on your trades and it's
one of the key principles of the DW
method which is how I trade so go and
check out that in the description box
and grab a notepad but let's bring this
back to the key Point here so when you
open these sorts of Trades you're
expecting to have a loss so when the
trade does lose and then you go and say
something like oh the trade didn't go
according to plan well that's not
actually true is it because you were
expecting the result was going to be a
loss and then it was but I have to admit
it feels a bit counterintuitive to open
a trade expecting it to be a loss and
still think that's a good idea but you
have to accept it and embrace it
otherwise you'll fall into this negative
spiral and end up just being like all
the other losers in the market and
here's what I mean when I say about a
negative spiral so a lot of Traders will
accept that they're trading asymmetric
risk rewards and it's more likely that
any individual trade will end up being a
loss and on paper that's all fine that
is until they actually start hitting the
losses and then all that goes out the
window they start hesitating doubting
their approach without realizing it they
start to self-sabotage they'll start
making changes to try and avoid losses
they'll tweak their system over adjust
things and end up with an inconsistent
mess rather than improving things
overall they'll just end up securing
themselves a negative Traders equation
and a massive L that they can hold if
you've been watching our videos for a
long time you'll already know that I
really like using Sports and allergies
so the one I've got lined up for this
situation it's like a striker who can't
score now if if you're old like I am
you'll remember when Fernando Torres
joined Chelsea and practically overnight
it was like he was so bad at scoring
that it seemed more like intentional
satire some might say that's just the
Chelsea effect London is red but what
happens when Strikers hit these dry
spells like Fernando Torres is that they
start getting into their own heads
rather than seeing it as just a
probability thing or just a temporary
dip in form they start overthinking and
over adjusting and rather than
continuing to do the right thing that
they were doing before they constantly
change things until they get themselves
into an absolute mess and their
confidence is absolutely shattered so
bringing it back to trading the key if
you're going through a Torres mindset is
to get yourself Back to Basics reconnect
with the probabilities of your trades
and understand How likely it is to go
through a losing streak when you're
trading with asymmetric risk rewards I
also see this all the time when Traders
analyze their data so let's say you've
been going through a bit of a slump like
you've not been getting the results that
you thought you would and so over the
last 40 trades you analyze what's been
happening and you've taken nothing but
trades with a 1 to four risk reward
ratio and with your system you're
expecting to have a 25% success rate
which overall would mean that you're
profitable but when you analyze those 40
trades you discover that your success
ratees only been 20% so what a lot of
Traders will do is they'll see that and
they'll think W 20% that is not good and
then they'll start worrying going into
this negative spiral and actually if you
just stop panicking and look at reality
you'd realize that 20% of 40 trades is
eight trades and 25% of 40 trades is
just 10 trades so that's the difference
of two trades and with a small sample
size of 40 trades you can expect some
variability and two trades is really not
that much so being blunt and totally
honest here if you are losing overall
with your trading it's very likely to be
because your trading approach is
just saying that's the case for most
Traders but before you jump to that
conclusion you have to understand the
probabilities of your trades and allow
your trading approach the chance to
perform you have to allow the expectancy
to play out over time before you can
really judge where you're at having the
right perspective is key for successful
trading and then once you've done that
for a long enough period of time and you
have a good enough sample size you can
start to analyze it to figure out if
something does need to be changed or not
and if you want to understand more about
what the right sample size is check out
this video next